Guide to the Middagh family papers 1974.179
Brooklyn Historical Society
Middagh family papers
1654-circa 1840
1654-1789
Brooklyn Historical Society
Middagh family
1974.179
0.17 Linear Feet in 17 folders.
The Middagh family papers (1654-circa 1840) contain a variety of documents, many linked to the Middagh family by name or by affiliated family, including Couwenhoven and Stryker.
Box A0013
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Sarah Gracie, 1867.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in rough chronological order.
Biographical note
Aert Middagh (circa 1707-1777), son of Gerrit Aertsen Middagh and Cornelia van Kowenhoven, married Magdalena Stryker (b. 1710), daughter of Jan Pieterse Stryker and Margretta Schenk. All of these surnames appear in the collection. For further genealogical information, see the item level inventory associated with the March, Middagh, and Sands families property records (1974.038).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Many property and other records related to the Middaghs and affiliated families can be found in the March, Middagh, and Sands families property records (1974.038).
Other Middagh family material is in: Middagh family agreement (1977.642) Garrett Middagh papers (1977.654) John Middagh account book (1974.027)
Other related collections include: Landon family papers (1977.025)
Scope and Contents
The collection contains a variety of documents, many linked to the Middagh family by name or by affiliated family. Many documents have no obvious relationship to the Middaghs. Most of the collection includes legal documents of various forms including deeds, bonds, agreements, and legal filings.
Among the documents are: the concluding pages (pages 5-8) of the 1825 correspondence from William Steele to his son concerning Jonathan Dayton's recollections of Benjamin Franklin's proposal for prayer at the 1787 Constitutional Convention; the articles of agreement between generals Burgoyne (British) and Gates (American) at Saratoga during the Revolutionary War (1772), signed by Burgoyne; plans for the building of a school in Huntington, Long Island, and the subscriber list (1762); a circa 1675 transcript of a 1669 Suffolk County Clerk's document regarding the testimony of several Indian sachems of Montauket relating to a land dispute concerning the Conklings; a testimonial of a committee of Boston preachers recommending minister Joseph Torrey (1732); an accounting of legal expenses charged in the case Aert Middagh v. John Middagh; and terms of sale on property mortgaged to Henry Landon.
Three items concerning African-Americans in Brooklyn are in the collection: an unidentified will (1727), an enslaved person's bill of sale (1737), and an arrest warrant concerning the unlicensed sale of liquor, including to African-Americans (1751). Aside from Middagh, among the names appearing in the documents are Couwenhouven, Stryker, and Thomas Tredwell (Suffolk County). Eight documents (1654-1702) are in Dutch.
The collection includes one outlier document, the terms of sale of property mortgaged by Isaac Conklin and George L. Conklin to Henry Landon. The document is undated, but is perhaps circa 1840, based on the dates concerning Henry Landon in the Landon family papers (1977.025). It is possible that this document was originally part of the Landon papers (received in 1866, less than a year before the Middagh donation) and was separated by mistake.
Agreements; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Kings County (N.Y.); Suffolk County (N.Y.); New York (State) |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783; Indians of North America -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Legal documents; Legal instruments; County courts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Deeds; Long Island (N.Y.); Slavery |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Correspondence; Real property -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Enslaved people -- bills of sale; Saratoga Campaign, N.Y., 1777; Real property |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Genealogy; Stryker family; United States. Constitutional Convention (1787); Torrey, Joseph; Cowenhoven family; Middagh family
- Dutch manuscripts, 1654-1704 (Box A0013, Folder 1)
- Suffolk County Clerk's office, 1669 (Box A0013, Folder 2)
- Brooklyn deed, 1684 (Box A0013, Folder 3)
- Garrett Middagh papers, 1696, 1706 (Box A0013, Folder 4)
- Brooklyn deed, 1702 (Box A0013, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous documents, 1707, 1746 (Box A0013, Folder 6)
- Will, 1727 (Box A0013, Folder 7)
- Massachusetts manuscript, 1732 (Box A0013, Folder 8)
- Aert Middagh, 1734, 1760 (Box A0013, Folder 9)
- Enslaved person bill of sale, 1737 (Box A0013, Folder 10)
- Brooklyn Board of Supervisors, 1750 (Box A0013, Folder 11)
- Brooklyn Justice of the Peace, 1751 (Box A0013, Folder 12)
- Huntington, Long Island school house building, 1762 (Box A0013, Folder 13)
- Revolutionary War Saratoga treaties, 1772 (Box A0013, Folder 14)
- Thomas Treadwell deed, 1789 (Box A0013, Folder 15)
- William Steele letter, circa 1825 (Box A0013, Folder 16)
- Conkling family, undated (Box A0013, Folder 17)